Baron Gracias

barongracias@gmail.com | +44 7561 313823 | linkedin.com/in/baron-gracias

SUMMARY

Data scientist with over **3-years** of experience in technology & payments, showcasing a track record of applying **Python**, **SQL** and **BI tools** to extract insights, deliver projects and make **data-driven decisions**. Strong ability to present insights and tailor communication to a wide range of audiences. Supported critical national infrastructure, explored economic crime, built reliable machine learning models, managed **terabyte-scale databases** and provided **£3m/year** analytics.

Skills: Python, Machine Learning, scikit-learn, pandas, seaborn, T-SQL, PL/SQL, ETL, Power BI, Git, CI/CD, A/B testing.

EXPERIENCE

Mastercard 2022 - Present

Data Scientist II

- Vocalink: reporting and analytics on the UK's critical national infrastructure real-time payments system (FPS, Bacs, ICS). Applying Python and SQL against TB-scale database to analyse trends and extract economic insight.
- Pay.UK: created an efficient & scalable rules-based model that classified 250m accounts as business or personal.
- Office for National Statistics: managed collaboration to enhance existing service, successfully deploying a random forest model with Python and oracledb that classifies 15m accounts per month with over 90% accuracy.
- Industry NLP: assessing financial movement between UK industries by similarity matching our transactional text data to Companies House with tfidfvectorizer and nmslib to achieve 95% accuracy for over 50m accounts.
- **UK Finance:** automated several regular reporting scripts by implementing **synchronous dependency** processes with Python; minimising points of failure, maintaining regulatory deadlines and resulting to **100%** report availability.
- **Financial Crime:** proof-of-value on phishing data provider; assessed feature vector similarity, early detection rate improvements and presented value-add by implementing **PCA**, **distribution** and **cluster analysis** with scikit-learn.
- BancNet EDA: explored the emergence of economic crime in the Philippines RTP network, extracted insights on early fraudulent behaviour and identified an instrumental detection feature which increased ROC AUC by 2%.
- Open Banking: produced a payment purpose and insights model showcasing rolling expenditure trends and statistics. Implemented into Open Banking offering and increased average sale value by £10k over 6 months.

Data Engineer I 2020 - 2021

- Vocalink Placement: upgraded GB-scale project delivery data warehouse, built ETL pipelines and BI analytics.
- Developed a **predictive** resource management model, allowing PMs to precisely book timesheets and maximise utilisation with an accuracy of **99.6%**. Up to **3x** increase in capacity and **£3m/year** in corrected project financials.
- Built high-impact **Tableau dashboards** providing a real-time view of global project KPIs and created a "**60-second**" daily summary board that enabled senior leadership to make rapid data-driven decisions.

PERSONAL

Sports Director: founded several Mastercard teams to compete in corporate charity events, managed a budget of £50k after successful pitches to C-suite. Donated over £20k for CRUK and represented USA at the FIFCO World Cup in Crete.

Conferences: representative at ConfX Analytics Summit Amsterdam, HPE Data Science London, and Big Data London.

EDUCATION

University of Bath 2018 - 2022

BSc (Hons) Physics

- Achieved high first-class: fine-tuned analytical and abstract problem-solving skills for loosely defined problems.
- Malvern Panalytical, Industry FYP: led a team of 4 to develop an HDR laser measurement system with OpenCV.

Certifications 2024

- Data Science Specialization, IBM, exploring core research methodologies and applications using Python, SQL, R.
- Machine Learning Specialization, DL.AI, covering core ML concepts in un/supervised and reinforcement learning.
- Machine Learning in Production, DL.AI, exploring best practices in ML deployment, monitoring and optimisation.